Guide to Culinary Ephemera: Flour Products, Leavening Agents, and Baked Goods ams.0058
University of Michigan Library (Special Collections Research Center)
- Leavening Agents
  - Box 49
    - A lesson plan on baking powder batters and doughs (revised). 10, [1] p., 1927 (Box 49, Folder 9)
      Item [9] is a teaching guide from R.B. Davis Company for teachers, food demonstrators, and culinary students. Includes history, chemistry, and preparation of baking powder batters and doughs.
    - The little book of excellent recipes and cooking tips / by the Davis mystery chef. 92 p., 1932 (Box 49, Folder 10)
      Item [10] promotes Davis Baking Powder and radio show of Davis mystery chef, aka John MacPherson. Includes recipes, household hints, and general cooking instructions. Sample recipes: mystery chef cake, Swedish kaldolmar, cocomalt pudding, and endive salad.
    - The little book of excellent recipes / by the mystery chef. 102 p., 1934 (Box 49, Folder 11)
      Item [11] promotes Davis Baking Powder. Includes recipes by mystery chef, aka John MacPherson; table of weights and measures; explanation of cooking terms; index; personal anecdotes; cooking tips; advertisement for Davis Baking Powder with product packaging illustration; household tips; picture of mystery chef's home; caricature of the mystery chef (front cover); and his endorsement of product (back cover). Sample recipes: pot au feu, jungle soup, and Scotch muffins.
    - Davis master pattern baking formulas. 80 p., 1938 (Box 49, Folder 12)
      Item [12] promotes Davis Baking Powder. Contains 146 recipes derived from variations of 21 "master pattern baking formulas" developed and tested by the Davis Company. Includes illustrations of serving suggestions and product packaging; detailed index; and illustrated baking techniques. Sample recipes: Snow White cake, jelly tarts, and plum pocketbook rolls.
    - Save money: use Health Club Double-Acting Baking Powder with these recipes. 11 p., 1932 (Box 49, Folder 13)
      Item [13] promotes Health Club Baking Powder as effective, economical, and healthful. Includes household hints; illustrations of product packaging, period dress, and NRA seal; and cartoon story reflecting societal norms, such as men living in boarding houses until they could afford to get married and own a home. Sample recipes: muffins, pancakes, and plain cake. Marked: L-1.
    - The cook's book. 47 p., 1926 (Box 49, Folder 14)
      Item [14] promotes K C Baking Powder. Includes recipes by Janet McKenzie Hill; beautiful color illustrations of period dress and serving suggestions; pictures of laboratory; cooking hints; money back guarantee; replica of award from U.S. Government to Jaques Manufacturing Company for World War I service; and embossed gold medal on back cover. Sample recipes: K C hot cross buns, K C cherry pudding, and K C nut cake.
    - Favorite recipes from the K C Baking Powder cook's book: [folded brochure]., circa 1931 (Box 49, Folder 15)
      Item [15] promotes K C Baking Powder. Includes illustrations of serving suggestions and packaging and baking hints. Recipes include K C waffles and K C doughnuts. Marked: Dept. C-B.
    - The cook's book. 47 p., 1933 (Box 49, Folder 16)
      Item [16] is similar to [14] except refers to prepared flour instead of self-rising flour. Describes award as distinguished service award and updates number of years in business. 2 copies.
    - Clabber Girl recetas: [folded brochure]., 1939 (Box 49, Folder 17)
      Item [17], in Spanish, promotes the use of Clabber Girl Baking Powder. Includes three recipes and illustrations of serving suggestions, product packaging, and period dress.
    - The cook's book: recipes prepared for K C Baking Powder. 31 p., circa 1941 (Box 49, Folder 18)
      Item [18] promotes K C Baking Powder. Includes large quantity recipes; testimonial to the company longevity as run by Jaques family; illustrations of patents and trademarks; endorsement from state fair winner; award from the U. S. government for World War I service; illustrations of laboratory, product packaging, and serving suggestions; and baking hints. Recipes similar to [14] and [16].
    - K C cook's book. 32 p., circa 1942 (Box 49, Folder 19)
      Item [19] promotes K C Baking Powder. Includes baking hints for ingredients, equipment, measurement, and mixing; product packaging and serving suggestions illustrations; introduction by Lorna Lee; and mail-in offer for additional recipe books. Sample recipes: hot cross buns and yellow corn bread.
    - Gold Label recipes. 16 p., circa 1941 (Box 49, Folder 20)
      Item [20] promotes Gold Label Baking Powder, made of highest grade ingredients, supervised by chemists, and previously manufactured by Hardesty Manufacturing Co. Includes cooking hints and gold metallic product packaging illustration on front cover. Sample recipes: Gold Label bran muffins and beef and lima bean stew with dumplings.
- Flour, Baking Powder, and Baked Goods
  Series 3: Flour, Baking Powder, and Baked Goods contians a mix of publications promoting those products, with dates from 1864-1976. Most publications are from the 1880s-1950s. Of particular note are two editions of the Rumford Almanac and Cookbook from 1886 and 1888.
  - Box 139.
    Hopkins, T., Dr.
    Hopkins, L. A., Mrs.
    Washington, Mary Ball.
    Hudson & Thompson.
    Hills Bros. Coffee, Inc.
    Cleveland Baking Powder Co. (New York, N.Y.)
    H.H. Warner & Co.
    Rust Craft Publishers.
    Ralston Purina Company.
    Casey's Cakes & Cookies, Inc.
    - Breads you bake, with yeast. 11 p., circa 1960s (Box 139, Folder 1)
      Item [1] promotes Gold Medal Better-for-Bread Flour. Includes step-by-step illustrated instructions for baking bread with yeast, quick breads, rolls, and sweet rolls; illustrations of serving suggestions and product packaging; and advice on baking. Sample recipes: Swedish limpa rye bread, quick buttermilk rolls, and Hungarian coffee cake. Marked: A11428.
    - Betty Crocker's foods men like. 28 p., 1976 (Box 139, Folder 2)
      Item [2] promotes General Mills products. Includes an alphabetical listing of recipes that men would like; some recipes using General Mills products (Gold Medal Flour, Bisquick, Potato Buds); and illustrations of serving suggestions and Peter Max-like pop art drawings of men (in spacesuits, doctor's coats, football uniforms, etc.) preparing to eat or carve food. Some recipes include wine, beer, or liquor as an ingredient. Booklet was published by Golden Press, price was 49 cents. Sample recipes: blueberry cobbler, oyster stew, and Wiener Schnitzel. Marked: ISBN: 0-307-09523-1.
    - Alabama Beauty self-rising flour: [leaflet]., circa 1930s (Box 139, Folder 3)
      Item [3] promotes Alabama Beauty self-rising flour packed by Hudson & Thompson. Includes eight cake, icing, and dessert recipes; illustrations of serving suggestions and product packaging; and a refund offer from grocer if customer is not satisfied with the product. Sample recipe: spice-pecan cake.
    - Gingerbread made from the 200 year-old Washington family recipe: [brochure]., circa 1940s (Box 139, Folder 4)
      Item [4] promotes Dromedary gingerbread mix from the Hills Brothers Company. Includes eight recipes using Dromedary gingerbread mix; information that the mix is based on the original recipe of Mary Ball Washington, the mother of George Washington, found in an ancient cook book written in her own handwriting; and illustrations of product packaging, serving suggestions, Kenmore mansion (home of George Washington's sister, Betty Washington Lewis), and Kenmore kitchen; and silhouette profile portraits of Mary Ball Washington and George Washington. Sample recipe: George Washington's gingerbread.
    - Touch your menus with magic by using Robin Hood all purpose flour: [folded brochure]., circa 1956 (Box 139, Folder 5)
      Item [5] promotes Robin Hood flour. Includes 5 recipes, attributed to Rita Martin of the Home Services Dept. of Robin Hood Flour; offers for aluminumware through the redemption of coupons in Robin Hood flour and for money back plus 10% from dealer if not thoroughly satisfied with the flour; and illustrations of serving suggestions, Rita Martin, woman in period costume, and aluminumware. Sample recipe: pink magic pie. Marked: series A-355.
    - Food for thought: Velvet Cake and Pastry Flour: [folded brochure]., circa 1950s (Box 139, Folder 6)
      Item [6] promotes Velvet Flour. Includes 3 cake and quick bread recipes; illustrations of man, girl and boy in period costume and merchandise available through the Velvet Thriftee Plan; and instructions on ordering Thriftee plan merchandise (using Thriftee coupons and cash) with descriptive catalog of available merchandise. Sample recipe: walnut loaf.
    - Cleveland's superior receipts. 68 p., 1891 (Box 139, Folder 7)
      Item [7] promotes Cleveland's Superior Baking Powder. Includes two recipes and a product endorsement from Sarah T. Rorer, principal of the Philadelphia Cooking School; recipes from church societies, friends, and patrons for soups, fish, meats, vegetables, entrees, salads, fish and meat sauces, puddings and pudding sauces, pies, desserts, cakes, bread and breakfast cakes, pickles, preserves and jellies, beverages, and for the invalids's tray; menu suggestions; illustration of product packaging; advice on how to test for ammonia in baking powder; list of 12 reasons Cleveland's Superior Baking Powder is the best baking powder; list of endorsements from government chemists, state officials, and professors of chemistry; citing of authorities against the inclusion of alum and ammonia in baking powder; list of baking powders containing alum or ammonia; stamp on back cover "With compliments of Overbeck & Staebler, Ann Arbor, Mich."; and index. Some recipes include wine, beer, or liquor as an ingredient. Sample recipes: mock bisque soup, smothered chicken, and apple snow. Damaged: pages 45 and 46 missing.
    - Science in the kitchen / by Dr. T. Hopkins and Mrs. L.A. Hopkins. 24 p., 1864 (Box 139, Folder 8)
      Item [8] promotes powders used as additives to flours. Includes information on superiority of these powders; instructions on preparing the flour; and recipes for breads, biscuits, cakes, cookies, puddings, pie, dumplings, donuts, buns, pancakes, and flapjacks. Sample recipes: Lincoln and Hamlin cake, Indian pudding, and clam pie.
    - Sea Foam's collection of dainty receipts. 28 p., 1907 (Box 139, Folder 9)
      Item [9] promotes Sea Foam Baking Powder. Includes information about Sea Foam Baking Powder; recipes for cakes, biscuits, muffins, fancy breads, griddle cakes, custards, cream, and chicken casserole; illustrations of product packaging; and index. Sample recipes: snow cake, Harlequin cake, and floating island.
    - The school lunch box: [folded brochure]., 1923 (Box 139, Folder 10)
      Item [10] promotes Royal Baking Powder. Includes luncheon and sandwich suggestions for the school lunch box from Educational Dept. of Royal Baking Powder Company; hints on attractive packing of lunches; menu suggestions; references to recipes in the Royal Cook Book; six recipes; and illustrations of children in period dress. Sample recipe: Scotch fingers. Marked: 2-24.
    - How to live better and save money. 20 p., circa 1950s (Box 139, Folder 11)
      Item [11] promotes Arm & Hammer Soda Bicarbonate. Includes suggested uses of the product as a health-aid, for cleansing, as a baby-aid, and for baking; four recipes; illustrations of product packaging, serving suggestions, and period dress. Sample recipe: applesauce cake.
    - Cooking recipes. 48 p., 1892 (Box 139, Folder 12)
      Item [12] promotes H.H. Warner products. Includes information on health and nervous conditions treatable by Warner's Safe Cure, Warner's Safe Pills, Warner's Safe Rheumatic Cure, Warner's Safe Nervine, Warner's Safe Diabetic Cure, Warner's Safe Asthma Cure, Tippecanoe, the Best, and Benton's Hair Grower; promotes the purity and use of Warner's Safe Baking Powder and Warner's Safe Yeast; offers for Warner's Safe Cook Book and to become a shareholder in H.H. Warner; recipes; testimonials from customers and medical journals; illustrations of product packaging, period dress, and, on front cover, a procession of Black native bearers in possibly African setting with palm trees and mountain; and index. Damaged: front cover detached and frayed, back cover almost detached. Sample recipes: turkey rissoles, wheat crumpets, and broiled snipe.
    - The yeast that keeps fresh: [brochure]., circa 1930s (Box 139, Folder 13)
      Item [13] promotes Yeast Foam from Northwestern Yeast Company. Includes instructions on use; information on why Yeast Foam is the preferred yeast among home breadmakers; suggestion to eat three cakes daily as a corrective foam to treat "constipation, boils, pimples, indigestion, auto-intoxication, run-down condition, etc."; offer for "The Art of Making Bread"; mention of "The Yeast Foamers", a radio spot on the N.B.C. Blue Network; illustrations of serving suggestions and product packaging; and three recipes. Sample recipe: white bread.
    - Oven melodies with Maca Yeast. 27 p., 1940 (Box 139, Folder 14)
      Item [14] promotes Maca Yeast from Northwestern Yeast Company. Includes instructions on use; recipes for breads, rolls, coffee cakes, cakes, buckwheat cakes, and root beer; offer for recipe book, free on receipt of 3 Maca Yeast wrappers; and illustrations of serving suggestions and product packaging. Sample recipes: gluten bread, jiffy rolls, and Swedish tea ring.
    - Sandwich recipes: [recipe cards]., circa 1910s (Box 139, Folder 15)
      Item [15] promotes sandwich recipes. Includes 18 3 inch by 5 inch recipe cards in an illustrated envelope folder with two pockets for the cards; illustration of women in period dress; and recipes for sandwiches and sandwich fillings. Item was distributed or printed by Rust Craft, a Boston greeting card company. Sample recipes: fresh tongue sandwich, Indian filling, and Saint Patrick sandwich.
    - This coupon is worth 10 cents in buying a package of Ry-Krisp: [coupon]., circa 1933 (Box 139, Folder 16)
      Item [16] promotes Ry-Krisp. Includes coupon worth ten cents with instruction to mail coupons to Ralston Purina Company, which will promptly send ten cents and postage and illustrations of product packaging and the NRA (National Recovery Administration) Blue Eagle logo. No recipes. Marked: C 2753 A - 9-32.
    - English muffins from Casey's: [folded brochure]., circa 1940s (Box 139, Folder 17)
      Item [17] promotes English muffins from Casey's Cakes & Cookies, Inc. Includes advice and recipes on preparing English muffins; suggestion to serve English muffins for breakfast, luncheon, and between-time snacks; and illustrations of serving suggestions, period dress, and an industrial moving griddle for baking English muffins. Sample recipe: open-face muffinburgers.
    - "Uneeda Bakers" Premium Sodas new meal-in-a-minute treats. 14 p., circa 1950s (Box 139, Folder 18)
      Item [18] promotes Premium Soda Crackers from "Uneeda Bakers", National Biscuit Company. Includes recipes using Premium Soda Crackers as an ingredient; illustration of N.B.C. Uneeda trade mark; and index. Sample recipes: blue ribbon herring salad, tick o' the clock salad, and prune pudding pronto.
  - Box 140.
    Taylor, Demetria, 1903-
    Hoyt, Barbara.
    Rice, Lilian Dynevor.
    Kintzing, Helen S.
    Christie, Robert.
    Baker, Mary Ellen.
    Rudkin, Margaret.
    Allen, Bailey Ida.
    Adams, Margaret.
    Hayward, Agnes Carroll.
    Davis, Betty.
    Hathaway, Ruth F.
    Harben, Philip.
    Colonial Baking Company.
    General Baking Company.
    Hall Baking Co.
    Mills Bakery.
    W. E. Long Co.
    Langendorf Baking Company.
    Christie, Brown & Company.
    John Bent & Co.
    Loose-Wiles Biscuit Company (Spokane, Wash.)
    Ward Baking Company.
    Purity Bakeries Corporation.
    Rhodes Refrigeration, Inc.
    Dakota Bake-N-Serve, Inc.
    Continental Baking Corporation (New York, N.Y.)
    Quality Bakers of America.
    Port Huron Bread Co.
    Sara Lee Corporation.
    Morphy-Richards (Cray) Limited.
    Marathon Corporation.
    Gase Baking Company.
    Carr & Co.
    Shaffer, Clarke & Co., Inc.
    - 20th anniversary colonial sandwich book / [Demetria Taylor]. 1v. (unpaged, circa 1930s (Box 140, Folder 1)
      Item [1] promotes Colonial white bread, Colonial rye bread, and Colonial wheat bread varieties of home delivered packaged bread. Introduction titled Sandwiches for every occasion by Demetria Taylor. Has illustrations of packaging. Inside rear cover illustration of door-to-door bread delivery truck and uniformed driver. Includes recipes for events, occasions, and holidays. Illustrations of serving suggestions accompany recipes. Sample recipes: sandwiches for the children, evening card party sandwiches.
    - Baking powder biscuits: [folded brochure], circa 1960s (Box 140, Folder 2)
      Item [2] promotes heat and eat packaged biscuits. Illustrations of serving suggestions accompany recipes. Sample illustrations: chicken-on-a-biscuit, fruit shortcake, and butterscotch surprise. Marked BK-99.
    - Bond Bread cook book. 22 p., 1933 (Box 140, Folder 3)
      Item [3] promotes Bond Bread brand of packaged bread from Bond Bakers. Introduction by Barbara Hoyt. Notes that they are the first to add vitamin D to bread--p.5. Includes table of vitamins in various foods, illustrations of packaging, and illustrations of serving suggestions. Sample recipes: Melba toast, Mexican rabbit, stuffed beef heart, and Yankee fluff.
    - Bond Bread cook book. 72 p., 1935 (Box 140, Folder 4)
      Item [4] promotes Bond Bread brand of packaged bread from Bond Bakers. Introduction by Barbara Hoyt. Includes illustrations of packaging, illustrations of serving suggestions accompany some recipes. Sample recipes: beets with sour sauce, spinach and egg croustades, and chocolate waffles.
    - A book of recipes and suggestions for the use of toast. [32] p., 1937 (Box 140, Folder 5)
      Item [5] promotes Super-Toast Bread brand of packaged bread from Mills Bakery. Claims to be the first exclusive toast recipe book ever. Includes suggested menus with approximate costs. Illustrations of serving suggestions accompany some recipes. Some recipes include canned soups and other packaged products, some recipes include wine. Sample recipes: deviled rarebit, cherry wine surprise, and pineapple toast delight.
    - There's a difference in bread. 15 p., 1922 (Box 140, Folder 6)
      Item [6] promotes Langendorf Royal Breads vairiety of packaged bread. Front cover illustration of child with bread and jam. Illustrations of serving suggestions accompany some recipes. Sample recipes: ribbon sandwich, tomato toast, scalloped crabmeat, and stuffed eggplant.
    - Biscuit in choice recipes. 1 v. (unpaged), 1921 (Box 140, Folder 7)
      Item [7] promotes packaged biscuits, cookies, and crackers from National Biscuit Company. Has list of products. Recipes attributed to Lilian Dynevor Rice. Front cover has illustration of child in rain coat, back cover has illustrations of packaging. Illustrations of serving suggestions accompany some recipes. Includes menus. Sample recipes: salt cod chowder, blushing bunny, and chocolate-nut pudding in Lotus Wafers cases.This item is exhibitable.
    - Menu magic. 16 p., circa 1932 (Box 140, Folder 8)
      Item [8] promotes Uneeda brand packaged biscuits and crackers, and other packaged biscuits, cookies, and crackers from National Biscuit Company. Introduction titled: The magic way to plan meals by Nancy Best. Illustrations of serving suggestions accompany some recipes. Includes menu suggestions. Sample recipes: hula moon pie, fish patties, and zwieback parfait. February 1932?
    - The fall book of menu magic. 24 p., 1932 (Box 140, Folder 9)
      Item [9] is similar to [8]. Includes "Penny-wise treats" section of budget recipes. Includes menu suggestions for events, occasions and holidays. Sample recipes: icebox cherry pie, quick chop suey. September 1932.
    - Menu magic. 24 p., 1932 (Box 140, Folder 10)
      Item [10] is similar to [8]. 2nd printing (revised and enlarged) April, 1932.
    - Winter menu magic. 24 p., 1933 (Box 140, Folder 11)
      Item [11] is similar to [8]. Introduction by Nancy Best. Includes "thrift menus" section of budget recipes and menus. Some recipes include liquor. Sample recipes: vegetarian loaf, Italian spinach, and pears Olga. Includes original mailing envelope with penny stamp and Uneeda logo. January, 1933.
    - National Biscuit Company's book of fifty delicious desserts. 16 p, 1938 (Box 140, Folder 12)
      Item [12] promotes packaged biscuits, cookies, and crackers from National Biscuit Company. Introduction by Helen S. Kintzing. Inside back cover illustration of packaging. Illustrations of serving suggestions accompany some recipes. Center spread illustration of cookies and crackers with names and descriptions. Sample recipes: mock bisque ice cream, zuider zee, and date and nut torte.
    - 15 rather ritzy recipes = 15 recettes de ritz: [recipe cards in box], circa 1970s (Box 140, Folder 13)
      Item [13] promotes Ritz crackers. Attributed to Mr. Christie.Likely from the Canadian operations of Christie, Brown & Co. Recipes are in French and English. Illustration of packaging. Illustrations of serving suggestions accompany recipes. Sample recipes: teeny pizzas, ritzy kids parties, and peanut butter crispies.
    - Famous New England dishes made with Kennedy's Special Commons: [folded brochure], circa 1950s (Box 140, Folder 14)
      Item [14] promotes Kennedy's special commons brand of packaged crackers from Nabisco. Sample recipes: Nantucket cracker pudding, Gloucester lobster stew, and scallop chowder.
    - A dozen and one tasty recipes made with Dromedary pound cake mix: [folded brochure], 1974 (Box 140, Folder 15)
      Item [15] promotes Dromedary pound cake mix from Nabisco. Some recipes include liquor. Sample recipes: elegant rainbow Alaska, Tosca torte, and baba au ruhm.
    - Dromedary date delights: [folded brochure], 1975 (Box 140, Folder 16)
      Item [16] promotes Dromedary packaged dates. Introduction by Mary Ellen Baker, Director of Home Economics. Front cover illustration of serving suggestions. Sample recipes: curried chicken skillet, fruited tuna salad, and macaroon pie.
    - A dozen and one tasty recipes made with Dromedary gingerbread mix: [folded brochure], 1979 (Box 140, Folder 17)
      Item [17] is similar to [14] but promotes gingerbread baking mix. Sample recipes: Caribbean spice cake, gingerbread tree ornaments, and Hartford election cake.
    - Margaret Rudkin's own story of Pepperidge Farm Bread. [12] p., circa 1940s (Box 140, Folder 18)
      Item [18] has front cover illustration of Margaret Rudkin, illustrations of bakers working. Notes that breads are hand kneaded. Includes tables of weights and measures, substitutions, oven temperatures. Recipes use bread, rolls, or stuffing mix as ingredients. Has list of products on back cover.
    - Menu magic with Pepperidge Farm stuffing recipes: [folded brochure], 1959 (Box 140, Folder 19)
      Item [19] promotes Pepperidge Farm Stuffing mixes. Back page illustration of packaging. Illustrations of serving suggestions accompany some recipes. Sample recipes: calico crab, meat loaf Italiano, and Bombay chicken.
    - Pepperidge Farm presents some highly interesting sandwich recipes. 1 v. (unpaged), circa 1960s (Box 140, Folder 20)
      Item [20] Promotes Pepperidge Farm breads. Includes section of hints for making sandwiches. Inside front cover illustration of Margaret Rudkin. Illustrations of serving suggestions accompany some recipes. Sample recipes: party sandwich loaf, western burger, and mosaic sandwiches.